<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook V5.0//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/docbook.dtd">
<!-- TODO:
 - Consider removing all hard line breaks in favor of adjusted Scribus templates
 - Should there be a separate construct for capitals to define them more clearly?
-->
<book>
<info>
  <title>Ada & Zangemann</title>
  <subtitle>A Tale of Software, Skateboards, and Raspberry Ice Cream</subtitle>
  <author>
    <personname>
    <firstname>Matthias</firstname>
    <surname>Kirschner</surname>
    </personname>
    <personname>
    <firstname>Sandra</firstname>
    <surname>Brandstätter</surname>
    </personname>
  </author>
  <copyright><year>2023</year><holder>Matthias Kirschner and Sandra Brandstätter</holder></copyright>
</info>
<preface>
  <title>Ada & Zangemann</title>
</preface>
<chapter xml:id="ch1">
  <title>Front Cover</title>
  <para>A Tale of Software, Skateboards, and Raspberry Ice Cream</para>
</chapter>
<chapter xml:id="ch2">
  <title>Imprint</title>
  <!-- TODO: Consider splitting this literallayout into multiple, perhaps with para tags -->
  <literallayout>
Copyright © 2023 Matthias Kirschner and Sandra Brandstätter.
This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License.
To view a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/ or send a letter to Creative Commons, PO Box 1866, Mountain View, CA 94042, USA.

<emphasis role="bold">Ada & Zangemann: A Tale of Software, Skateboards, and Raspberry Ice Cream</emphasis> is a translation of the German original, Ada und Zangemann: Ein Märchen über Software, Skateboards und Himbeereis, published by Dpunkt.verlag in cooperation with O’Reilly Media, Inc., under the imprint “O’REILLY,” © 2022 by Matthias Kirschner and Sandra Brandstätter.

First printing

26 25 24 23 22 1 2 3 4 5

ISBN-13: 978-1-7185-0318-2 (print)
ISBN-13: 978-1-7185-0319-9 (ebook)

Publisher: William Pollock
Author: Matthias Kirschner
Illustrator: Sandra Brandstätter
Managing Editor: Jill Franklin
Production Editor: Jennifer Kepler
Editor: Wiebke Helmchen
Color Assistance: Olga Biryukova, Noémi Sárkány, Nathalie Scattolon, Kristina Haidinger, and Jasmin Schlögl
Cover Design: Sandra Brandstätter and Susan Brown
Compositor: Maureen Forys, Happenstance Type-O-Rama

For information on distribution, bulk sales, or corporate sales, please contact No Starch Press, Inc. directly at info@nostarch.com or:

No Starch Press, Inc.
245 8th Street, San Francisco, CA 94103
phone: 1.415.863.9900
www.nostarch.com

A catalog record of this book is available from the Library of Congress.

No Starch Press and the No Starch Press logo are registered trademarks of No Starch Press, Inc. Other product and company names mentioned herein may be the trademarks of their respective owners. Rather than use a trademark symbol with every occurrence of a trademarked name, we are using the names only in an editorial fashion and to the benefit of the trademark owner, with no intention of infringement of the trademark.

The information in this book is distributed on an “As Is” basis, without warranty. While every precaution has been taken in the preparation of this work, neither the author nor No Starch Press, Inc. shall have any liability to any person or entity with respect to any loss or damage caused or alleged to be caused directly or indirectly by the information contained in it.

All characters in this publication are fictitious, and any resemblance to real persons, living or dead, is purely coincidental.

**

This book by Matthias Kirschner (author) and Sandra Brandstätter (illustrator) is licensed under <emphasis role="bold">Creative Commons CC-BY-SA</emphasis>, a free cultural license.

<emphasis role="bold">You may</emphasis> share, copy, and redistribute the material in any medium or format. <emphasis role="bold">You may</emphasis> adapt, remix, transform, and build upon the material for any purpose, even commercially. <emphasis role="bold">You must</emphasis> give appropriate credit, provide a link to the license, and indicate if changes were made.

<emphasis role="bold">You may</emphasis> do so in any reasonable manner, but not in any way that suggests the licensor endorses you or your use. If you remix, transform, or build upon the material, <emphasis role="bold">you must</emphasis> distribute your contributions under the same license as the original. (This is a human-readable summary of - and not a substitute for - the “legal code” of CC-BY-SA 4.0.)

Furthermore for remix versions (derivative works), the licensor asks you not to make any modifications of the author's personal acknowledgments and the author's and illustrator's short biographies, instead please completely remove those parts from your remix version.

Publication under this free cultural license was possible due to the great support by dpunkt.verlag GmbH / O'Reilly Media, Inc. for the German book and No Starch Press for the English book. Unfortunately, Creative Commons licenses are still rare exceptions for commercially published books, and often considered revolutionary and risky by publishers.

<emphasis role="bold">A big thank you</emphasis to <emphasis role="bold">dpunkt.verlag</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">No Starch Press</emphasis> for understanding the values of software freedom, taking the time to discuss and understand the advantages of free cultural licenses, and the great support to publish this book under conditions that respect the FSFE's values.

<emphasis role="bold">Free as in freedom not price</emphasis>

Free Software is about the freedoms you receive with the software, not about the price. Likewise publishing a book under a free culture license does not mean you have the right to get a gratis copy of the book or ebook. It means you get the rights described above, which enable society to benefit further from this book, as it should from all cultural works.

We encourage you to support authors, publishers, and others involved in the creation of culture under free licenses – including <emphasis role="bold">financially supporting them through purchases or donations</emphasis>. (https://fsfe.org/donate) Society should support those who respect others' freedom.
  </literallayout>
</chapter>

<chapter xml:id="ch3">
  <title>Ada & Zangemann</title>
  <para>
Matthias Kirschner
Sandra Brandstätter

ADA & ZANGEMANN

A Tale of Software, Skateboards, and Raspberry Ice Cream
</para>
</chapter>
<chapter xml:id="ch4">
  <title>Zangemann and computers</title>
  <literallayout> <!-- NOTE: In order to maintain hard line breaks -->
    <inlinemediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="figs/print/capital-O-red.png"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
        <!-- TODO: additional information might be required for good screen reader support https://git.fsfe.org/FSFE/ada-zangemann/issues/50 -->
        <phrase>O</phrase>
      </textobject>
    </inlinemediaobject>
nce upon a time, there was a little girl named Ada. Her family was
so poor that all their savings fit inside a cookie jar. They didn’t have
enough money to live in a proper home. Instead, Ada lived with her mother and her little brother, Alan, in a cabin near a junkyard on the edge of town.
  </literallayout>
  <figure xml:id="ada-p04">
    <mediaobject>
      <!-- NOTE: that conditions for files could be used here -->
      <imageobject condition="print">
        <imagedata fileref="figs/print/ada-04.png"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject condition="web">
        <imagedata fileref="figs/web/ada-04.png"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
      <phrase>Ada in foreground leaving the house to go to school, in the background Ada's house and the junkyard. Ada has a brown backpack with yellow shoulder straps. To the left of Ada there is a red car, a Volkswagen Beetle, without wheels and no longer working, with one of the headlights remaining attached only with its wires. On the left, in front of the car, there are two tires, two boxes – one of which is a wooden box with an overturned bucket –, and an empty can, all among some plants with yellow flowers. In the background there is Ada's house, with her mother and her brother Alan waving goodbye, and the dog sitting on the ground. Alan is sitting on the two entrance steps of the house. He has short dark hair and is dressed in a white short-sleeved shirt with a red stripe at the edges of the sleeves and two red stripes at the bottom of the shirt. Alan wears blue shorts and he is barefoot. Ada's mom has dark lipstick and long black hair in a white headband. She is wearing a short blue shirt with white trim, white pants, and yellow shoes. Ada's house is built of wood, with the front being white. The roof is dark red corrugated sheeting. There are two windows in front in addition to the door, and another window on the left side. A yellow duck stands on top of the roof, while a gray chimney protrudes. An antenna on the left of the roof supports a clothesline on which red clothespins hold a green tank top, a pair of light blue pants, and white underpants. To the right of the house there is a veranda on which there is installed a solar panel. Under the veranda there are a mattress, a red oil drum, and a gray case. Behind the house there are piles of landfill objects among which you can see a washing machine, a car, and various wooden boards.</phrase>
      </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
</chapter>

<!-- NOTE: Perhaps this should just be a regular chapter, as acknowledgements normally are earlier in the book. -->
<acknowledgements>
  <title>Acknowledgments from the author</title>
  <para>Many thanks to Reinhard Wiesemann from the Linuxhotel for the financial support and motivation to no longer plan but to make. Thanks to Sandra Brandstätter, who has brought me joy with every new design for the illustrations. Thanks to my editor Wiebke Helmchen, who made developing and sharpening the story fun, and to No Starch Press for agreeing to publish the book under a free culture license.</para>
  <para>Thanks to Bea and Benni, Brian, Christine and Marc, Cory, Bernhard, Isabel and Amelia, Katta, Kristina, Martin, Mona and Arne, Nina, Oliver, Reinhard, Sabine, and Torsten for great ideas, inspiration, and practical tips, and to the many people of the Free Software movement, from which I was allowed to learn and whose engagement motivated me.</para>
  <para>For the English edition, I would like to thank John for his valuable feedback to improve the language, as well as Catharina, Pam, Till, and Vint for assisting me in figuring out how to get the book published.</para>
  <para>Thanks to my family, who made me write early in the morning, late in the evening, and on holiday, and who always supports my work for software freedom. Especially, I would like to thank my children, who inspired me with new ideas at each reading. Without them, this book would not exist.</para>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="figs/print/ada-51.png"/>
    </imageobject>
    <textobject>
      <phrase>Ada's dog wags its tail after finding Zangemann hidden behind a curtain and eating an ice cream cone with candies and a blue umbrella on it and lots of raspberry ice cream dripping.</phrase>
    </textobject>
  </mediaobject>
</acknowledgements>

<appendix>
  <title>About the illustrator Sandra Brandstätter</title>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="figs/print/ada-53.png"/>
    </imageobject>
    <textobject>
      <phrase> Sandra has always liked crafting with scissors, pliers, glue, wire, fabric, and paper. Today she works as an illustrator, comic author, and character designer for animated films and series, such as the German public television series Trudes Tier. On an ice-cream machine, Sandra would pick a creamy rainbow ice cream with lemon cucumber flavor and a lot of sprinkles.</phrase>
    </textobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <para> Sandra has always liked crafting with scissors, pliers, glue, wire, fabric, and paper. Today she works as an illustrator, comic author, and character designer for animated films and series, such as the German public television series Trudes Tier. On an ice-cream machine, Sandra would pick a creamy rainbow ice cream with lemon cucumber flavor and a lot of sprinkles.</para>
</appendix>

</book>